Hi, welcome back to Lam Rim.
We start with episode number 9.
I like to call it
"A Visit to the Middle of the Sun".
We've been talking about
something big and pretty powerful--
like a nuclear bomb used to clean ketchup
off your clothes or something.
And I'm not exaggerating.
I want you to think like that.
Imagine--
so today in America, it's Independence Day.
I'm talking about Independence Day.
Often we go on picnics with family.
It's the middle of summer.
And American kids will eat a hot dog
or a hamburger and they'll add too much ketchup,
and a little drop of ketchup will fall here.
Imagine that to clean it, mom sent a shirt or blouse to the middle of the sun
...
to clean a little tomato sauce, red ketchup.
I know it sounds like a strange image,
but I want you to try to think about it.
I want you to try to think about that.
I don't know what can compare it.
Yeah, I don't know.
Put a small object in the middle of the sun, okay?
So we're going to visit the middle of the sun today.
And I'm happy to announce that we've just reached the third and final section of the lam rim.
Steps to enlightenment.
As now we will enter
into the activities of bodhisattvas.
We will go into the way of
thinking and acting like a bodhisattva,
which is the highest capacity.
kyebu chenpo (KYES BU CHEN PO)
Which means a person with great capacity.
For those of you, especially those who have been following this lam rim for the past ten years,
you should be super happy that you survived
and I survived to the end.
We are at the final part.
This is the third and final part.
Well, the mathematicians among you should be thinking, Geshe-la,
you said there's 25% left.
So why is this the third and final part?
And the answer is that the treatment
by Pabongka Rinpoche on the last two days of
lam rim was too short.
His presentation on meditation
and seeing emptiness, the
last two of the six perfections, is
not very long.
And I don't know what happened.
I mean, sometimes--
it's like the sponsor comes to him and says we're going to run out of food in two days.
Finish it!
Maybe--
maybe this is a mystical message from Tara.
Maybe, I don't know,
maybe he has an appointment in another city.
But if you ask me, Pabongka Rinpoche
made the last two sections shorter because
Je Tsongkhapa already covered everything in his big Lam Rim.
"The Great Book of
Steps on the Path to Enlightenment,"
Lam Rim Chenmo
Tsongkapa did such a great job that I think,
I can see Pabongka Rinpoche saying,
you know,
there's not much reason for me to teach this section
because Tsongkhapa already taught it,
and he's wonderful.
There are many stories about
Tsongkhapa writing those last two sections
and I'm very happy
that we're going to do it together.
So we're going to finish this lam rim series
with these wonderful teachings on meditation and emptiness.
So that's why the section on the steps on the path for people who have bodhichitta,
for Bodhisattvas, is
not as long as it should be.
So here we come in.
Let's read the Tibetan text.
sumpa kyebu chenpoy lam gyi rim (GSUM PA SKYES BU CHEN PO'I LAM GYI RIM)
par lo jang wa la (PAR BLO SBYANG BA LA) Let
's train our hearts in the steps on the path
for people with great capacity.
People who are  Bodhisattva.
thek chen gyi juk go sem kyed kho nar ten pa phen yun dang cey pa (THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO SEMS BSKYED KHO NAR BSTAN PA PHAN YON DANG BCAS PA)
He said we will cover
this bodhisattva way of life,
we will cover it in three different steps.
Number one.
thek chen gyi jug go (THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO)
If you want to enter the bodhisattva path,
there is only one way to get there.
And that is by achieving a certain state of mind.
If you want to gain enlightenment,
if you want to have the opportunity to gain enlightenment,
if you want to have the opportunity to help the world, there is
only one way.
You must have bodhichitta.
You must have the desire to attain enlightenment
in order to be able to help countless beings.
Now, I want to talk about something that is countless.
Bodhichitta is aimed at countless sentient beings.
It is not aimed at everyone in your city or everyone in your country or all  people on this planet.
Zoom in--
if we want to send a virus to the center of the sun,
if we want to visit the center of the sun,
get out of the idea that we're working
for everyone on this planet.
No. Get out
of the idea that we're trying to help
all the fish and all the birds and all the animals
that walk on dry land.
No.
That's not the point.
We're encompassing the entire universe.
We decided today that I want to help
every living being in the universe.
Every little virus.
Bacteria.
Every whale.
Every human being in the universe.
So go out at night in Sedona, or outside of Sedona--
Rim Rock is better.
And look at the stars and try to imagine.
So first, you can't practice the bodhisattva way of life
if you don't expand your mind for it, for that purpose.
And if you actually experience it,
which takes some practice,
if you actually send your mind--
if you can actually get bodhichitta,
then the things you have to do in this world are nothing.
Nothing. Meaningless.
To help everyone in this world, that's not  nothing.
Easy.
phen yun dang cey pa (PHAN YON DANG BCAS PA) means
I want to tell you the benefits of thinking like that.
That's the first step.
jang chub tu sem kyed pay tsul (BYANG CHUB TU SEMS BSKYED PA'I TSUL) The
second step.
How do you get this breakthrough?
Mental Breakthrough?
How do you see the whole universe
and all beings in it?
And then develop love for them.
Is that possible?
That's the second step. The
third step.
semkye nay chud pa la lob tsul lo (SEMS BSKYED NAS SPYOD PA LA SLOB TSUL LO)
We will learn how to behave like a bodhisattva.
Once you have the wish to become a bodhisattva
then what to do?
How do I use my time and day
if I want to behave like a bodhisattva?
What should I do?
What is my schedule plan?
Okay. This is the first one.
dang po ni (DANG PO NI,)
de tar kye bu chung  dring gi kab su ngenjung gi sam pay kun nay lang (DE LTAR SKYES BU CHUNG 'BRING GI SKABS SU NGES 'BYUNG GI BSAM PAS KUN NAS BSLANGS)
So now that we have gone through the steps for people with lower and middle capacities,
at least you should have a feeling that
this life really is pain, this life really is trouble.
The virus just makes it obvious.
But it has always been like that. There has
always been a virus called death.
This virus is a new one. It is much smaller.
But at least now we all think about it.
hlak pay lab pa sum la bed pay (LHAG PA'I BSLAB PA GSUM LA 'BAD PAS)
We should
work on three wonderful trainings.
Treating others well.
Taking time for meditation.
And then try to see
that things do not come from their own side.
bed pay rang cig pu ('BAD PAS RANG GCIG PUS)
thar way go phang (THAR BA'I  GO 'PHANG)
thob tzam dang khor wa (THOB TZAM DANG 'KHOR BA)
len dok tzam jung (LAS LDOG TZAM 'BYUNG)
You can achieve nirvana on your own
and you can step off the Wheel of Life.
If you practice those postures as far as you can, it's possible.
We've taught you, we're done with it.
de tzam gyi mi chok (DE TZAM GYIS MI CHOG)
But I don't want you to stop
there. I don't want you to stop there. I want you--
there are bigger fish to fry.
There are much bigger fish to fry. Don't stop there.
pang ja tham ced ma pang (SPANG BYA THAMS CAD MA SPANGS)
If you only follow what I've taught you so far,
you won't cleanse your heart
of all the dirty things there.
thob ja yun ten (THOB BYA YON TAN)
tham ced kyang yong su ma dzok pay (THAMS  CAD KYANG YONGS SU MA RDZOGS PAS)
And you haven't achieved
all the highest spiritual qualities
that you can achieve.
ma dzok pay (MA RDZOGS PAS)
Therefore
rang dun dang (RANG DON DANG,)
shen dun yang nyi tse wa lay min jung (GZHAN DON YANG NYI TSE BA LAS MI 'BYUNG)
nyi tse wa (NYI TSE BA) that's a very disappointing word here.
It's a very sad word here.
It says you can work on the path that I've taught you so far,
you can do
all the meditations that I've taught you so far,
but the good that
you'll do for yourself and for others
is just a tiny fraction of what you need to do.
(NYI TSE BA) means it's just a tiny fraction
of what you need to do.
And by the way, the common usage of that word is the Tibetan word for hell on earth.
Which is very strange.
So there's a big hell that people go to.
But I always think of people who have car accidents and their cars explode and catch fire.
In  The ancient scripture is called
nyi tsi way nyal wa (NYI TSI BA'I DMYAL BA).
A small hell in this place. In this real world.
And this word nyi tsi wa means just a small piece.
And it says here, you want to help yourself
and you want to help others.
All I've been teaching you for 10 years is...
nyi tsi wa.
This is just a small part of what you can do, and now we're ready to start the serious stuff.
Now, Geshe-la, why did we spend 10 years doing nyi tsi wa, the small things?
Why don't we just go straight to the higher things?
Because the small things are the ladder
that helps you reach the higher things.
You can't reach the higher things
unless you do the other two parts.
Unless you practice all the steps in the lam rim
in the right order,
you'll never get to the bodhisattva part.
So, you can't say I don't want it.
Part of the bodhisattva way of life is mastering the lower paths that help you get there.
And you never refuse.  them.
You just grow from there.
mi jung shing lar thek chen (MI 'BYUNG ZHING SLAR THEG CHEN)
la shi nay juk gu la (LA GZHI NAS 'JUG DGOS LA)
This is an idea in Buddhism,
that as soon as you are ready,
and as soon as you have the preparation,
you should jump right into the
bodhisattva way of life
because otherwise--
you will have to do it again,
sooner or later, you have to get here.
Maybe during this lifetime.
Maybe in the next lifetime.
People come to me from time to time and say I'm going to take a break from this dharma.
I feel like I need a break.
I have other things to do now.
I have a big project at work.
or I have family problems right now
and I need a break.
I told one of my teachers once when I was in India, I remember
45 years ago.
And I said, "I have to take a break," and they looked at me and said, "Yeah, okay, but you'll come back."
You'll come back because there's nowhere else to go.
You'll come back. You'll come back because you have to come back here.  Life will bring you back here.
Because that's life. You need the lam rim.
Life will always bring you back to the lam rim.
Unless you die.
And it will still bring you back there later.
lar (SLAR) means you have to come back again.
lar thek chen la shi nay (SLAR THEG CHEN LA GZHI NAS)
shi nay (GZHI NAS) means you'll waste a lot of time
if you have to come back there.
You might as well finish it now
instead of coming back later. The
next picture here
is a little something.
I wanted to do it with you in this episode, episode 9.
I call it "A Visit to the Middle of the Sun."
So in this picture--
I was trying to find a picture that was close
to what it feels like to have bodhichitta.
So this picture looks a little--
we say, Seiji and I and Tim,
we say it's a little new-age. It
looks like it was painted in Sedona, Arizona.
It feels a little new-age, but listen.
If you've ever achieved bodhichitta,
this will feel...
this picture is very close. This photo is almost the same. Can you make it more  High? Just for a moment?
This picture isn't crazy,
and it's not some kind of hippie thing.
When you achieve bodhichitta, real bodhichitta,
it feels like this.
So maybe you want to make a copy of this photo.
We've paid for it.
So you can use it at home. You can keep it at home.
You can keep a photo like that.
Maybe put it on your screensaver on your phone. It's
pretty close to what it feels like to have bodhichitta.
So I want to take you on a little journey just for fun, maybe five minutes.
Let's review what it feels like—
when you first achieve real bodhichitta.
So we're not talking about approximate—
what do you call it? Partial bodhichitta.
Or trying to feel like you have bodhichitta.
Let's talk about the real thing.
When you see emptiness directly
and you immediately feel bodhichitta,
let's go through that because that's a good fortune.
And that's an atomic bomb.
If you keep working on it, if you keep working on this,
on the feeling, if you keep listening to this part,
it will help destroy the virus.
I believe it will help destroy the virus.
It's like a nuclear weapon.
And this virus is like a soy sauce stain.
So  Here we go.
Let's try to imagine for five minutes
what it would be like to attain bodhichitta.
Let's begin.
Let's take ten slow breaths.
Focus on the exhale, a long exhale, don't worry about the inhale; your body will breathe.
So please imagine
that you have just seen emptiness directly.
And you come out of direct perception,
and you return to what we might call normal meditation, which is still not in the world.
You are in deep meditation,
you are still on the cushion. Your
eyes are closed.
Then suddenly, in the forefront of your mind, an
image of your mother appears. This is your mother.
A very perfect image of your mother. A living image.
It's actually your mother.
Maybe you should remember her.
She looks like that now.
She looks at you.
She looks into your eyes.
Even though it feels like she's in the forefront of your mind, she looks into your eyes.
With great love and also a sense of need.
She desperately needs help.
She's in trouble.
Like she jumped off the Titanic or something,
and she looks at you with those eyes.
She says, "I need you, I need help."
And then you say to her out loud in your heart,
"Don't worry, Mom, I'll take care of you."
And I will.  Strong enough to take care of you.
Don't worry.
I'll have the strength to help you,
and I will, I promise.
And then the picture fades to the front of your mind, and suddenly there's an image of your dad.
And you're looking at your dad.
And he has that same look in his eyes.
It's a kind of hope, but also fear.
So he's looking at you like,
"Can you help me?"
Things are getting tough in life, life is hard now.
And then you say, "Dad, don't worry.  I'll take care of it!
I study lam rim.
I learned a lot about emptiness.
And I actually know I'll have the tools
to help you soon.
So don't worry.  I'll take care of it.
I'll take care of it."
And please don't-- don't be
afraid. Don't worry.
I know what to do and I'll do it.
Everything will be fine, so don't worry!
And then maybe someone else close in your life, your
wife or husband or children,
one of your children,
their image comes to the front of your mind.
Just their face.
And they're also looking at you like, "Can you help me?  Bad things, really bad things!”
Deadly things, there’s no hope.
Can you help me?
And you say, “
I can handle it, I will handle it.
I can.
I will have enough strength to take care of you.
You don’t have to worry.
I know what’s going on.
I know your situation.
I know what life is like.
I’ve found it
and I’ll take care of you completely.
Don’t worry.
You don’t have to worry.
I’ll take care of it.”
And then the face fades and then you start to fill in the faces of people you know.
Close people, close family.
Uncles, aunts.
Brothers and sisters.
Nieces.
One by one, you take them out
and you comfort them.
And you say: “Indeed, I will take care of him.” There’s
nothing to worry about.”
And in this way we solve everyone you know.
Everyone you have ever met in life.
Then you start working on all the people you haven't met and all the people in this whole world.
Start with your own environment.
Go to the city, the whole city, and you know, it's not like you can cover everyone.
But take someone here and take someone there
Take to the beach on this continent you live on.
Protect everyone.
And then go further.
To another continent.
And in this way we cover everyone in this world.
Just sit here.
And then you can start with the
animals in this world, on fish.
I'm not talking about any kind of animal.
I'm talking about helping each individual animal.
Each one is staring at you.  Everyone expects.
Each one is afraid.
Each one gets your personal guarantee.
"I'll take care of it. I'll take care of it."
Then imagine encompassing every little creature, the little creature on the sea floor.
Tiny creatures in your bloodstream.
Meet one on one.
Talk to them.
And when you finish all the living beings in this world,
we will start on the next world.
I don't know where the next world is.
I don't know what Alpha Centauri is?
Maybe light years away.
Go there and start doing the same meditation
for everyone in that world.
And in this way we cover every world
in the entire universe.
And karma meets one by one
each of the seven billion humans,
and trillions of other beings on one planet,
and then covers as many planets as there are.  Countless planets.
Encompassing every being there,
it is bodhichitta.
That is the direct experience of bodhichitta.
So please, for this episode,
if you can only get the feeling.
You don't need to worry about yourself.
You don't have to worry about your family.
You really don't have to worry about your country.
And you don't have to worry about the world being covered by viruses.  It's the little things!
We will take care of them.
We are working on a bigger project.
We do it to help the entire universe.
Countless billions of creatures.  There are
countless billions of animals and other creatures.
And we have that capacity.  You have that capacity.  I pray that you achieve that in this life.
I pray that you achieve it in this life.
Your mind already has the capacity to touch every living being and promise them that you will take care of them.
So the purpose of this lam rim,
the purpose of this retreat,
is kind of like to journey to the center of the sun.
Think of every living creature.
Many creatures live in the infinite universe.
Meet them one by one.
Promise one by one.
That is what happened
during the first direct experience of bodhichitta.
This really happened.
That's how it feels.
If you keep imagining it,
it will help it happen.
Really!
So it's up to you if you want it to come.
If you really want to be a real bodhisattva,
then practice.
Practice this visualization once or twice a day.
Only if you have a few minutes.  Just imagine.
In your imagination.  Okay?
And that will help make it happen.
And you will attain bodhichitta.
Then something like a virus, for a bodhisattva type, this virus is not a very important thing.
This is a very small thing.
Make money.
Earn a living.
Feed your family.
Looking for an apartment.
These are very small things.  There is
n't anything.
Your mind is like--
your heart is like the center of the sun.
And some...I don't know...a little cake or some coca-cola in the sun, it doesn't matter.
That's not important.
Look for the big thing!
Everything else becomes small.
And everything else becomes comfortable.  Easy.
That's bodhichitta.
Okay!
See you in the next episode.
Episode 10.